<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the witness of God manifested in me from my youth.</title>
            <author>Ames, William, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3004A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170294</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578119</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578119</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172081</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75294)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172081)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2613:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the witness of God manifested in me from my youth.</title>
                  <author>Ames, William, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: William Ames.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Quaker authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Quaker authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172081:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172081:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION OF THE WITNESS OF GOD <hi>Manifeſted in me from my YOUTH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom my Youth I was made ſenſible of ſomething in me which was contrary to God: but that which made it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt I knew not to be of God; although it was the ſeed of God in me which was Light, which made manifeſt my deeds to be wrought in darkneſs: for from that time that I was ten yeares of age, I knew Sin: but I knew not God: yea and before that time I knew it, but in many yeares after I knew not God: for when I would Lye, there was ſomthing within me which told me lying was a ſin, &amp; ſwearing was a ſin, &amp; evill ſpeaking, and deceitfull dealing, and fighting, and backbiting, and ſuch like was contrary to God; and it did not only diſcover ſuch and ſuch names of things unto me which were eivell, but it made the nature of them manifeſt unto me when they were acted, either by my ſelfe or others: this ſhewed me that Lying was to ſpeake falſly, Drunkeneſs, was to drink too much, and ſo ſorth; and when I had Lyed, then it would reprove me, or dealt deceitfully, it would laye open it to me, ſo that at all times when I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mited evill this was ready to Condemne me, &amp; this was alwaies contrary to the evill and many times Terrors of endleſs Torments was laid before me: inſomuch that I was reſtrained many times from accompanying with my familiers, and delighted to be alone: and ſomthing in me deſired to know God: this I witneſſed before I knew the Letter of the Scripture: but as I grew in yeares, I grew in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and the wicked one grew ſtronger and ſtronger in me, and the juſt grew weaker and weaker: So that I came to delight more &amp; more in ſin, and that which before reproved me, I found to be dead, then all my delight was in drunkenneſs, and uecleanneſs and was given up to Commit ſin with greedineſs: yet at ſome times I was ſhewen what I had don: But that which made manifeſt I knew no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:172081:2"/>After this I began to give ſome heed to the Prieſts of the World and heard them declare of a God and of a Chriſt which muſt be beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in for Salvation, and through Faith I muſt be ſaved, and Faith was to beleeve that Chriſt was the Son of God, and that he was Crucified for our ſins, and roſe again for our Juſtification, and then I began to ſearch the Scriptures and I grew up in the knowledge of the Letter, and did beleeve according as the Prieſts told me, &amp; there I thought my ſelfe to be ſafe, for when I was Convinced of ſin in my Conſcience, I was not long without a remedy, for there was not any promiſe in the Scripture which was to beleevers, but I could aply them unto my ſelfe becauſe I did beleeve that Chriſt dyed at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> and was buried, and the third day roſe againe &amp;c. In this State I continued for ſome yeares, yet ſtill takeing pleaſure in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: but could ſpeake much of the Letter of the Scripture, at the laſt I came amongſt a people called <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and was diligent in hearing them, and was much taken with their words: and deſired to be in fellowſhip with them, which was granted me; then newneſs of Life was required of me, by ſomthing within me which I knew not, but in that ſtate I was not able to attaine unto it, and although I was Baptized with water, yet repentance from dead workes I could not witneſs; but I grew much in the wiſdome and became a ſpeaker amongſt them: Yet that which I Preacht down in others, was upheld within my ſelfe; and ſo whilſt I preacht to others I was Condemned my ſelfe by that in my Conſcience; for that told me ſin was alive in me, and that I was under the power of darkneſs, and many times when I was tempted to Commit uncleanes ſomthing within me would ſhew me the Tempter, and the temptation; yet I found not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny power to reſiſt it: but with violence of luſt was carryed away to Commit it, and then ſomthing within me would mourne and groan under theſe Abominations ſo that ſomtimes Teares would proceed from mine eyes, yet a remedy I knew not, for that eye with which I ſhould have beheld my Saviour was blinded by the God of this world: and in this State I was Choſen to be an Elder, becauſe of my Wiſdome in the Letter: and when I was ſo, there was none ſo forward as I to condemn Sin, and yet my ſelfe the greateſt ſinner, &amp; would condemn them for not waſhing according to the rule, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture; whilſt I my ſelfe was Condemned in my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be an Enemy to God: Then many times the Saints faillings
<pb facs="tcp:172081:2"/>would be preſented unto me, to comfort me in that State, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in many times I tooke Courage and comforted my ſelfe in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: which I acted privatly, then as I grew higher in my wiſdome I began the more to conforme to the Letter of the Scripture for the Scripture declared againſt anger, then I began to abſtain from it outwardly; and uncleanneſs, filthyneſs, and deceit outwardly, and pride outwardly, and ſo many of the branches of Sin were Cropt off: but the Root and ground from whence it proceeded was not moved for when my will was croſt I was filled with anger, and that remained in my heart and Luſt had its abideing place within me, &amp; my heart was puft up with Pride: and deceit lodged within; and yet in this State I could ſpeake of Saints, and of waſhing and clenſing, and purifying by the Blood of Chriſt, Redemption, and Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sanctification, and Holineſs, all theſe things I could ſpeak of, and ſo the deceit which was out of the Life of the Saints, in the Curſe got the Saints words for a Covering, &amp; perſwaded me that there was no freedome from Sin untill I was dead, and then that faith which I had while I lived, by that I ſhould be ſaved when I was dead: So that Faith which purifyeth the heart I was a Stranger to, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes when the witneſs of God Convinced me of Sin in my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the deceit drew out my minde from it, to looke upon a Chriſt without me: and to minde the Scripture to be my rule, then many times it would be manifeſted to me wherein I walked Contrary to the Scripture, and contrary to the Saints walkings; then the deceit would perſwade me that the Scripture did not declare how they did walke, and how they were, but how they ſhould walke; and how they ſhould be, but never any of them did attaine to what they ſhould be; and therefore Chriſt dyed, that his Righteouſneſs might be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto us, and ſo we only beleeving in that ſhould be ſaved; and ſo God did not look upon us as we were ſinners, but he looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us through his Son who had borne his indignation for us, &amp; this was my Covering: And the Enemy got a place of abode within un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moleſted; and was transformed into an Angell of Light, Crying up the Ordinances of Chriſt, the Ordinances of Chriſt, Baptiſme, and breaking of Bread; and all that were not in this way were Iudged to be in the Kingdome of Satan, And out of the way of Chriſt. And ſo with the Saints words I was painted, but to the Life of the Saints I was a ſtranger: for the Croſs of Chriſt I knew not, but the enmity
<pb facs="tcp:172081:3"/>remained alive within me by which I was ſhut out from God, and his Covenant of Light I knew not, yet in this ſtate I was called a Miniſter of the Goſpell: and an Adminiſtrator of the Ordinances of Chriſt, when I was a ſtranger to his Light, and an Elder of the Church, when I never witneſſed a Childs State. And ſo in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition I continued, having a high Conceit of my ſelfe and outwardly many evills I had left, with which the world lived in; becauſe the Scripture declared againſt them, &amp; not becauſe I had a Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, which witneſſed for God againſt them, but was a Sranger to it and yet in my fallen wiſdome which was ſenſuall and diueliſh I had got the Saints words to ſpeake of, but the ſpirit which they had, by which they gave them forth I knew not not; And ſo in this Nature which is eſtranged from God, and is an enemy to him was our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, and being in this Nature we called our ſelves a Church of Chriſt, and Saints, when I knew not what a living Stone was: And I being in this State, many times that in my Conſcience would tell me that I was not a member of Chriſt, for I never witneſſed the new Birth, and ſomtimes this would ſtrike Terror in me, and then it would be preſented unto me that an Elder muſt be blameleſs, &amp; that in my Conſcience would lay open the wickedneſs of my heart, and let me know that I was not blameleſs, and that would let me ſee that the hand of the Lord was againſt me for I had only the forme of Godlineſs, but power I wanted by which Sin might be overcome, &amp; the good <hi>I</hi> was a Stranger to with which I ſhould overcome evill, as ſaith the Scripture: Be not overcome with evill, but overcome evill with good; and ſo Sin had Dominion, evill thoughts had Dominion Luft and Anger &amp;c. And although I had Cropt off many branches in my will that my profeſſion might not be ſhamed before the world, (which made it ſo much the more deceitfull, becauſe of its faire out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide) yet the Root remained and the earth ſtood by which it was nouriſhed, and the Ax was never layde to the Root, no it never came neere it, but there it ſtood firme unmoleſted for the Devill had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded me I ſhould never be freed from Sin whilſt I lived, &amp; much leſs from evill thoughts, and I beleeved him, for he had made me blinde that I ſaw nothing to the contrary; and ſo in the height of my profeſſion whilſt I ſay'd I was a Jew, my heart was the Sinagogue of Satan, and that he might get a peaceable habitation to Reigne as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> within me. He taught me to looke without me, for
<pb facs="tcp:172081:3"/>Salvation and take the Prophets words, and the Saints words to be my rule; for he perſwaded me that there was no other rule in theſe dayes, or way to know God; then that which they had left in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo he having perſwaded me herein, he obtainted his end; for I looking out with my firſt nature and falen wiſdome (run) unto the Letter of the Scripture, and ſo in that nature which is under the power of the devill and accurſed from God, I had got a profeſſion of words; and ſo I fed upon winde, but all this while the devill had his deſire; for the ſeed of God which was Light within me, which let me ſee my Sin I knew not, though ſomthing convinced me of Sin, yet I knew not what it was; for the God of the world, who ruled in my heart had blinded my Eye, with which I ſhould have ſeen my Redeemer; and ſo the ſeed of God was kept in Captivity, and death reigned even over that which had not tranſgreſſed, and the beloved of God (the Light) was delivered into the hand of the devourer; and the Juſt was opreſſed: And ſo whilſt I had took upon me the Name of a Saint I was an Enemy to God: Looke (here you higheſt of profeſſors behold this is your ſtate) at laſt the Lord was pleaſed to begin his worke in me, and did let me ſee that the longer we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in our profeſſion, the more wickedneſs and Confuſion we grew into, and there was ſcarce any Sin that was Committed by the world: but it was to be found amongſt us, who called our ſelves Saints; as Pride, Covetouſneſs, Luſt, Envy, Eivill-ſpeaking, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Lying, Vaine-Jeſting, Idle-talking &amp;c. That in ſtead of grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up in purity, we wrew up in Impurity; differing nothing from the World, only in our profeſſion, then I ſaw the vanity of all profeſſion, and being out of all profeſſion. Yet I knew not that which ſhewed me the Vanity of it; for the wicked one having poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of my heart, kept my minde from that which ſhewed me the deceit of my heart, and the deceit of all profeſſion; and perſwaded me that there was no God; and led me out into liberty to follow my own hearts luſt; but ſtill there was ſomthing within me though very low which did bear witneſs againſt Sin, but I knew not what it was although many times I was terrifyed with it, but it was his everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing love that in this State I continued not long; for there being one who was ſent by the Lord to declare his name whoſe Miniſtry I wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be of God declared: that that which Convinced man of Sin, was the light of Chriſt with wch he had enlightned every man that
<pb facs="tcp:172081:4"/>Commeth into the world, &amp; this Doctrin peirced through me, yea it peirced through the earth and never ceaſed untill it read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the witneſs which lay in the grave under death which was covered with earth, this heard the voice, and knew the voice, &amp; owned the voice, and did ariſe out of the grave, then that which had kept it in bondage even the ſame which had got the Saints words to ſpeake of, and had made a profeſſion was diſmayed, and feareſulneſs layd hold upon that nature, &amp; that would have fled from the preſence of the Light but I turning my minde to within to the Light, ſaw my ſelfe polu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, a den of Theeves, a Cage of unclean Birds, a habitation for Dragons; and the Sinagog of Satan: Then did the Juſt ariſe in fury and indignation then was the Sword drawn, and made ready for the ſlaughter, and the everlaſting Arme was ſtreched out againſt the heathen to cut down and to deſtroy, and make deſolate that great City Babilon, which had laid Gods heretage waſte; then did he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe in his power, and did ſlay on the right hand, and deſtroy on the left; then did her young Men fall in the Streets, and her Men of War were Cut off, and her ſtrong ones did faint, and her mighty ones were diſmayed before the preſence of the Lambe that was dead and is alive, and liveth for ever more; for his hand did not ſpare neither did his eye pitty, untill he had avenged himſelfe of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaryes, and had goten himſelfe a Name above all Names; and ſo keeping my minde to that of God, which was manifeſted in me, I Came to ſee the giving out of the Law, which was dredfull to that Nature which had Sinned, which Law was Light, by which Light, I ſaw my ſelfe, and my nakedneſs was diſcovered, and Gods Judgments made manifeſt againſt the tranſgreſſor; then rotenneſs poſſeſſed my Bones, and my fleſh did ſtink, and a noyſom ſore brak-forth upon me, and all my joy was turned into mourning and bitter Lamentation; for there was no way to eſcape the Sword, if ever I came to the tree of Life; for it turned every way, and the ſeaven Thunders vttered their voyces, and the ſeaven Plagues was powered forth upon that Nature the man of Sin: So here I came to witneſs the Lord to enter into the houſe of the Theefe, and to be a ſwift witneſs againſt the Sorcerer and all evill doors. And ſo as I kept my minde to the Light, I came to witneſs my redemption and the firſt Nature to be deſtroyed, for as I came to minde the Light, I minded the Law of God which Law is Light, which Law I found
<pb facs="tcp:172081:4"/>writen in my heart, and ſo keeping my minde to that which diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered Sin, I received power againſt Sin, &amp; my minde being kept to that, mine eye was ſingle &amp; my whole body was full of Light, ſo that I could ſee the enemy, and comprehend his wiles, and ſee the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and ſee that Nature which had joynded &amp; would joyne with the tempter, but ſtanding in the Light, I ſtood in that which croſt that Nature and did abide in the Counſell of God, and through this Croſs that nature was ſlain, and a dying to Sin, I came to witneſs through the Light and I had no more need to be taught of Men or to looke without me for a theacher, for this ſhewed me what was good; &amp; what the Lord had required of me, and when I looked out and gon from it, this would reprove me, and let me ſee wherein I had offend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed and this would riſe up in Judgment againſt the offender &amp; I keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my minde to it the wicked could not eſcape, nor the deceiver could not be hid, for the things of Eſau were ſearched out, &amp; his hiden things ſought up, and I found the Lord watching over me to pluck up and to throw down, and to make waſte the habitabion of Eſau, and here I came to witneſs a Diſciples ſtate, for my minde being kept to the Light, I was upon my watch-tower, and there I could ſee the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, for the Light made him manifeſt and every vaine thought was brought to Judgment, and the houſe of Ioſeph was a flame, and the houſe of Eſau as ſttubble, and the houſe of David grew ſtranger &amp; ſtronger, but the houſe of Saule grew weaker and weaker; and here I came to know the terrors of the Lord againſt that which had ſinned and the Man-Child came to be borne, which nothing could ſatisfie but the Bread of Life: and God gave me Manna from heaven, fro it to feed upon, and it was fed and grew ſtrong in Battle, ſo that he ſlew on the righ hand, and deſtroyed one the left; and his Name became dreadfull to his adverſaries, for all judgment was given unto him, &amp; as he did over come, then pure joy would ariſe and the living would praiſe him from whom deliverance came. And here I came to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Faith by which my heart was purified, and by which I over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the world, which faith is the gift of God, to which faith, in the higheſt of my profeſſion I was reprobate as all the worlds profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are, for I only beleeved becauſe it was Writen; and ſo my fallen wiſdom and firſt Nature which is accurſed being ſound in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion beleeved the report of a thing as of God and Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me, but I did not beleeve in the Light as Chriſt Commanded
<pb facs="tcp:172081:5"/>who ſaith beleeve in the Light, that you may be Children of the Light, but to this Light I was a ſtranger and an Enemy, my minde being alianated from it, looking for a Saviour without me, when when the Enemy of my happineſs which alone I had need to be ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from, was within (O! all profeſſors read your conditions) and ſo the doore to the Father which is the Light, I was an Enemy unto, and ſo an Enemy to God being an Enemy to his Light; for how could I be reconciled to God whilſt I was condemned for Sin in my Conſcience by that meaſure of Light which he had given me to walke by, which is a meaſure of himſelfe that Condemned me, then how could I be juſtified by him who is one with his Light, and ſo the reconciliation which the Saints witneſſed I knew not, untill my Sin came to be taken away by Chriſt, the Light; then I came to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Salvation by Jeſus who ſaved me from mine Enemy, mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was Sin, he ſaved me from Sin, the ſting of death is Sin, in ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me from Sin I was freed from death, and the ſtrength of Sin is the Law; in ſaving me from Sin, the righteouſneſs of the Law was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in me, who walked not after the fleſh. Take notice the fleſh did not lead me but after the ſpirit; Take notice againe by the ſpirit I was led, and and the ſpirit is Light which leadeth not into Sin, but into righteouſneſs, and being led by the ſpirit I had peace with God; the ſpirit is Light, following the light, obeying ths light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving in the light, I was by the light reconciled to God, and by Chriſt the light, the middle wall of Partition was broken down and he was my Peace, the light. Heare all you profeſſors of the World are ſhut out, whoſe minde is from the light, he is not your peace whilſt you commit Sin, for Sin is reproved by the light, and that which is reproved is made manifeſt by the Light.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILLIAM AMES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Printed in the Yeare 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
